RG 003, New London County, County Court Files
Connecticut State Library
One of the major trends that occurs in the period after 1790 and is reflected in court records is the growth of corporations, like banks, insurance companies, turnpike companies, cotton manufactories, and railroads. The General Assembly chartered the first banks in 1792. Bank lawsuits begin in November 1794 when the Union Bank of New London sued ten debtors. The records contain around 400 lawsuits involving banks. Although some thirty banks are represented by at least one court case, a handful of banks from the region predominate. In addition to the Union Bank, they consist of the Norwich Bank, Washington Bank (Westerly, Rhode Island), New London Bank, Stonington Bank, Thames Bank (Norwich), Whaling Bank (New London), Merchants Bank (Norwich), Quinebaug Bank (Norwich), and Jewett City Bank (Griswold).25
Insurance companies, both marine and fire, are represented in around sixty cases. The first two in November 1803 involve the Norwich Marine Insurance Company. The owners of the sloop Thetis sued the company for $1,000 to pay for damages suffered by the vessel on a voyage from Gibralter to Savannah off the coast of South Carolina. The court deemed the declaration of the plaintiffs insufficient and they appealed to the Superior Court.26 In the second case, the company sued Christopher Raymond of Montville on a debt by note.27 In the bulk of the lawsuits, plaintiffs seek compensation for losses at sea. By the 1840s, however, the cases concern fire losses, as in Langdon & Smith v. Merchants and Farmers Fire Insurance Company of Worcester for a fire loss of more than $800.28
Corporate growth in 19th-century Connecticut finds reflection in close to 100 cases involving cotton manufacturing, the earliest dating from the War of 1812 era.29 The first case found dates from June 1813, Danielson Manufacturing Company v. James N. Barber, a debt by book for cloth and thread.30 The famous pioneer Samuel Slater is a defendant in a covenant broken lawsuit over running the machinery at the Jewett City Cotton Manufacturing Company.31
The early national period was marked by great interest in transportation improvements, first by turnpike companies, then by canals, and thirdly by railroads. Court files contain more than eighty lawsuits concerning highways and turnpike companies. In the former category, defendants were usually towns that had violated a Connecticut statute, "Providing for Altering, Regulating & Mending High Ways," as in a December 1788 suit in which Jacob Avery sued the town of Groton to collect £30-7 damages for a highway laid out more than a decade before that crossed the plaintiff's lands.32 In some twenty-six cases, a turnpike company was party to a lawsuit, most involving the Hartford and New London Turnpike Company (9 cases), Norwich & Woodstock Turnpike Company (4 cases), and New London & Lyme Turnpike Company (4 cases). In addition, the court heard some half dozen lawsuits involving the New London & Newport Assurance Stage Company between December 1801 and November 1802, about a dozen cases concerning bridges and toll bridges, about the same number with the Norwich Steam Boat Company, and two June 1824 ones with a horse team ferry.
Railroads destroyed the turnpike companies in less than a generation. Between 1837 and 1855, some fifty presentments involving railroads were filed before the county court. The bulk concerned three railroads; the Norwich & Worcester Rail Road Company (26 cases), New London, Willimantic and Palmer Rail Road (12), and New York, Providence, and Boston Rail Road (7). Corporate records for many of the first railroads are virtually non-existent, thus a small number of court cases potentially have great research value.
A great variety of other subjects are discussed in the Files and it is possible only to provide a hint of the rich resources found in these records. After debt cases, the second largest quantity of cases found in New London County Court records revolve around land disputes. The controversy may be over inheritance to land, the seisin and possession of land,33 leases to farms or dwellings, or such other subjects as disputes over fencing between two property owners and trespass.
Partition of land cases has particular relevance to those with a genealogical perspective because the names, relationships to other family members, and residences of all parties in the lawsuit are 34. To cite just one example, the court heard an extremely complex case involving the grandchildren of Joseph Rogers (1646-1697) of New London in February 1742. The plaintiffs consisted of five heirs of John Rogers, deceased, son of Joseph, and the defendants were three heirs of James Rogers, deceased, son of Joseph. Also named in the case were the other seven children of Joseph Rogers and a number of heirs of these children.35
In the February 1767 case of Richard Deshon et al v. Lancaster Comstock, the plaintiffs sued for the seisin and possession of a lot of land or messuage at Black Point in Lyme, property that originally belonged to John Prentiss the elder, together with £100 damages.36 The plaintiffs recovered judgment and the defendant appealed.37 In a second case that same session, William Hilliard v. Ebenezer Cobb, the plaintiff sued for the seisin and possession of twelve rods of land and a dwelling house from which he had been removed by force the preceding May. The declaration of the plaintiff was deemed to be insufficient and the defendant recovered court costs.38
An example of a dispute over a lease in found in November 1773, Mary Pierpont v. John Denison 2d. In May 1771 the defendant leased a 40-acre farm in Stonington for two years for rent of 24 shillings per year, but he never paid the rent. The defendant defaulted and the plaintiff recovered £2-8 debt and £1-9-9 costs.39 Many lawsuits over leases were listed in the records as covenant broken, as in two June 1818 cases. In the first, William Keeney of Waterford sued to collect $70 in unpaid rent on leased land in Montville, while the second concerned a fifty-year lease for an iron works, mill dam, and stream in Lyme.40
The records contain hundreds of cases of trespass. Many consist of lawsuits for illegal cutting of timber, tearing down fences, and cutting and harvesting crops on the land of plaintiffs, although in other instances, the trespass was assault and battery, defamation, theft, or some other crime.41 In one of many accusations of illegal cutting of timber, Samuel Willard v. Abraham Andrus, the court found the defendant guilty of cutting down seven good white oak trees from the plaintiff's land in Saybrook.42 In John Rogers v. Samuell Davis, the defendant was accused of breaking down walls of a cellar that was going to be part of a house. The plaintiff recovered £65 damages.43 In November 1733 case, William Ely of Lyme charged William Brockway with trespass, specifically cutting three acres of grass on the plaintiff's land "near the mouth of Eight Mile River." In another instance, Richard Manwaring (New London) v. Jonathan Beckwith in June 1740, the defendant was accused of borrowing an ox and working it too hard in the heat, so that it subsequently died.44 In Samuel Hull v. Thomas Trapp demanding £100, the plaintiff stated that the defendant owned a dangerous mare prone to kick and bite people. Despite this knowledge, the defendant carelessly let the mare loose at Norwich Landing, it kicked the plaintiff's four year old daughter and broke her skull. She died two months later. The case was withdrawn, perhaps because the defendant agreed to pay £10 in medical costs.45 In 1827, Peter and Henry A. Richards sued Lorenzo Dow of Montville. They claimed that the defendant had expanded a huge "Cotton Manufactory" on a stream they shared and so enlarged the dam as to damage the plaintiffs' grist mill to $2,000 damages.46
Another significant type of case consists of lawsuits against or by county sheriffs, deputy sheriffs, and town constables, the men who served summonses and writs of execution. If a legal officer failed to properly serve a writ or summons, then he could be sued. In one such case, Jeremiah Lattouche and Joseph Haynes of New York sued Constable Richard Burch of New London in June 1740 for ?270 damages due to his failure to serve a writ. The court found the defendant guilty, the plaintiffs were to recover ?270, and the defendant appealed.47
The November 1755 saw the case of Edmund Quincy (Braintree, Mass.) v. Christopher Christophers, sheriff of New London County. The plaintiff charged that Christophers had failed to recover 186 ounces of silver per writ of execution against John Whiting and John Hallam of Stonington. Christophers confessed judgment and was order to pay to the plaintiff 175 ounces of silver.48 In other instances, following a writ of execution, personal property or livestock of a defendant was seized to pay the judgment and legal costs. Normally, the constable or deputy sheriff seized the property and turned it over to a neighbor on the promise that the property would be delivered to the constable at the town signpost in thirty days at which time the property would be sold at auction. In November 1772, constable Prosper Wetmore of Norwich sued Daniel Kelley and Lemuel Warren for the return of ten hundred weight of iron valued at £20 that the plaintiff had seized by a writ of execution against Joseph Kelley. Wetmore recovered judgment for £14-6-2 damages and £1-1-7 costs.49 Or, a constable or deputy could be accused of false arrest, as in the case of Gideon Fitch (Norwich) v. Nehemiah Waterman, Junr. "Being in ye Peace of God," the defendant with force and arms arrested the plaintiff, took him five miles to jail, and detained him for three days. Fitch demanded £200 damages, but the pleading of the defendant was deemed sufficient and the plaintiff appealed.50
The court issued hundreds of writs of scire facias summoning defendants and their sureties to appear to answer charges brought against them.51 Many writs were issued in fornication cases, as in November 1731 against Lydia Chapman of Saybrook for failure to answer a summons to appear.52 Then there was the case of Dom Rex v. Mary Fanning, wife of Jonathan Fanning, Jr., for incontinency before marriage. Mary did not appear before the court and neither did her husband and a writ of scire facias was issued against Jonathan, Jr. as surety for his wife's appearance.53 Or, Dom Rex v. John Stocker. Stocker from Middletown was accused of abusing and threatening Joshua Raymond, Esq. of New London. He failed to appear, his bond was forfeited, and a writ of scire facias issued.54
Similar in nature are lawsuits instituted by the country treasurer against defendants and their sureties who failed to appear at court and forfeited their bonds. The February 1848 court heard five suits filed by Jacob W. Kinney against defendants and sureties who failed to appear on charges of adultery and assault.55 In an earlier case, Sheriff Prosper Wetmore sued the administrators of the estate of Jason Fargo of Norwich, former jail keeper, for £1,000 for allowing two prisoners to escape. The plaintiff recovered almost £20 damages and court costs.56
The records of the New London County Court contain for the pre-Revolutionary period 550 cases that can best be characterized as sexual crimes. The accusation may be for fornication, adultery, incontinence before marriage, lascivious carriage, or keeping a bawdy house.
Two patterns are typical, particularly for the fornication cases that make up the bulk of these cases. The first constituted lawsuits instituted by the King's Attorney against a female for a crime, and second, a wronged female suing the male source of her troubles. Lurana Knight was found guilty of fornication in November 1723 and sentenced to be fined or whipped.57 In June 1738, Mary Leffingwell v. Samuel Story, Jr., the plaintiff stated that she was begotten with child by fornication by Story. The court found Story guilty the previous November, but the defendant asked for a review and this time the court found for the defendant.58 Atypical, however, is the case of Grace Hewitt v. Phineas Stanton, Jr., both of Stonington. Grace charged that the defendant had promised to marry her and that the couple had courted, but that "the Pl[aintif]f in an unguarded hour yielded to his Importunities in the gratification of his unlawful Desires." She became pregnant, her intended deserted her, and Grace sued for £500 damages. The court agreed with her claim and ordered Stanton to pay £500 damages plus court costs. The defendant appealed his conviction.59
The first of about twenty adultery case found in Files dates from November 1710. Lyme grand juror Samuel Peck brought Thomas Bradford and Meriam Merrow, wife of Henry Merrow, before two justices of the peace on suspicion of adultery. One witness testified that she saw "mistris merrow lye upon her back her Cloath [sic] being up; her lower parts was nacked: Leftenant Bradfords briches was downe about his heels and sd Bradford was then Laid upon her." The two defendants were bound over to the county court.60 One of more than forty lascivious carriage cases is that of Dom Rex v. Capt. Nichols and Mary Wilcocks. Nichols was a transient man and master of a ship and Wilcocks, a single woman. The presentment stated that Wilcocks turned up her Clothes and uncovered the most Secret parts of her body" and Nichols "laid his body on her." Nichols pleaded not guilty but the jury found against him. He was fined £15 and whipped ten stripes "on his naked body.61 In Dom Rex v. Bathshua Cleveland (New London), the defendant on the presentment of grand juror Ephraim Brown was accused of maintaining a "house of Bawdery and Incontinency" in the absence of her husband. She pleaded not guilty before a local justice of the peace, was bound over to the county court with a £10 bond of recognizance, failed to appear at court, and thus defaulted on the bond.62
The records include almost 400 cases of assault, profane swearing, turbulent and threatening behavior, and riot for the period to the American Revolution. A representative assault and battery case is that of Gideon Brockway v. Allen Christophers, Caleb Mumford, and George Colefax. The plaintiff was attacked while walking on the highway to New London with clubs and staves and sued for £100 damages. A jury found the defendants guilty and ordered them to pay the plaintiff £20 damages and £7-7-11 court costs.63 In the June 1726 case of Dom Rex v. Thomas Stoddard of Norwich, the defendant was convicted of "using profain Discourse" and sentenced to the New London house of correction.64 In a case of turbulent and threatening behavior, Joseph Page of Stonington accused constable Gilbert Fanning with force and arms, viz, clubs, staves, "and other terrifying weapons" of breaking into the plaintiffs barn and seizing two hogs worth £2. The plaintiff asked for £2 damages but the case was withdrawn.65 A case on the November 1767 docket, Dom Rex v. Peter Bowdish, Rufus Branch, Samuel Branch, Edward Mott, Nathaniel Larabee, and Alpheus Jones, all of Preston, saw the defendants charged with "riotously Routously and unlawfully Assemble... being armed With Clubs [and] Staves" and assaulting Benjamin Freeman. The defendants confessed their guilt, each were fined 10 shillings, and had to pay court costs of £5-19.73
Almost 200 cases of theft have been found and when one combines these with numerous cases of trover and conversion and those in which plaintiffs state that certain real property has gone out of their possession by some unknown means and into the hands of the defendant or property was described as being casually lost, the total is impressive.67 In Dom Rex v. Daniel Hammond, a transient person, the defendant was convicted of stealing £100 of goods from the shop of Zebulon Elliot of New London. He was whipped ten stripes, order to pay court costs of £5-15-7, and pay a 20 shilling fine to the county treasurer.68 In Nathaniel Peabody v. Stephen Johnson, the plaintiff made a plea of trover and conversion for possession of a brown mare, while in Caleb Gates v. Moses Kimball, the plaintiff in a plea of trover and conversion stated he was the owner of two-thirds of a sawmill and iron works worth £10 that had by some unknown means come into the possession of the defendant.69 In June 1772, Henry Babcock of Stonington sued Amos Chesebrough for the return of three bottles of claret that were in the possession of the plaintiff in March, but came into the possession of the defendant and were not returned.70 Finally there is the case of John Harvey v. Thomas Anderson, both of Lyme. The plaintiff casually lost two heifers that had come into the possession of the defendant. He sued for £5 damages.71
Table 1. Civil Cases, 1781-1855
1781-1789 66 26 32 32 68 5 229
1790-1799 63 9 49 7 22 13 163
1800-1809 119 4 42 12 19 19 215
1810-1819 116 5 61 24 9 6 221
1820-1829 99 2 78 33 10 11 233
1830-1839 92 4 85 41 8 9 239
1840-1849 51 1 43 23 6 0 124
1850-1855 30 1 47 19 6 4 107
Totals 636 52 437 191 148 67 1,531
The table provides important data on perceived civil wrongdoing. In addition to the number of criminal prosecutions for assault, an almost equal number of civil prosecutions for the same offense exist. The civil assault prosecutions include over sixty instituted by mariners who were beaten by the masters or mates on the high seas, an indication of the violence that could occur on shipboard. The June 1782 court heard three such cases, all against the crew of the sloop Unity.73 Although the records hold a comparatively small number of civil prosecutions for theft, if one adds the number of cases on trespass in which personal property, livestock, timber, and other agricultural products were seized with force and arms; the number of cases in which goods went out of the possession of the plaintiff or were casually lost and came into the hands of defendants; and the cases of trover and conversion and replevin, then the total is impressive. The Other category consists of civil prosecutions for offenses often prosecuted by the State Attorney, like arson, counterfeiting, forgery, gambling, illegal night walking, horse racing, stage performances, and tumultuous carriage.
The records are equally valuable for those with a biographical or genealogical focus, for court records contain a great deal of information on hundreds of people that cannot be found elsewhere. Often a single case will bring a previously unknown individual to life, but frequently persons are represented by a series of cases, making it possible for the diligent to flesh out an individual's life.
The Rev. Stephen Gorton, pastor of the Baptist Church in New London, has been in part the subject of one scholarly article. The General Meeting of Baptist Churches suspended him in 1756 for "unchaste behaviour with his fellow men when in bed with them." The article reference made to a June 1726 trial before the New London County Court for sodomy, but we learn little else about Gorton.74 A careful examination of court records, however, reveals that Gorton was plaintiff, defendant, gave a deposition, or is mentioned in some twenty-five cases between 1726 and 1773. Several cases revolve around his role at a Baptist minister and one from February 1773 is of particular interest. In Stephen Gorton v. Pardon Tabor, the plaintiff sued the defendant for assault and battery. Gorton claimed that he was attacked with a large stick while preaching from the pulpit and sued for £1,000 damages. The defendant argued that Gorton was guilty of lascivious and sodomatical practices, that in 1767, 25 or 30 male members of the congregation had withdrawn from the church, and that the plaintiff had agreed to no longer serve in his ministerial office provided the male members halted actions of an ecclesiastical council against him. Tabor argued that Gorton had violated this agreement, but was nonetheless convicted. He appealed. 75
Another such person is Benedict Arnold, the father of the Revolutionary War general and traitor, who died a bankrupt and drunkard, and whose fate is supposed to have greatly influenced his notorious son. Arnold was plaintiff or defendant in some 55 cases between 1737 and 1756. One can see the final collapse in 1756, when he was sued for and confessed judgment to debts totaling some £13,000 in depreciated old tenor currency. In one case, the Norwich constable attached a huge quantity of personal property, property that included Negro servants - Peg, Dinah, Bristo, and Philip. Arnold was ruined and died in 1761.76
The records are also valuable for helping to determine identity in an era when several people could share the same name and in listing a trade or profession. The records contain several cases in which Jonathan Rogers sued Jonathan Rogers. In February 1730, for example, Jonathan Rogers, son of James Rogers deceased, and further identified by the word "shop" [blacksmith] brought suit against Jonathan Rogers, son of Samuel deceased, "wood" [wooden leg].77 The records also tell us that John Beckwith was a shipwright, Richard Brockway a mariner, Benjamin Gale a merchant, William Lamson a carpenter, Joseph Lothrop a glazier, and James Rogers a cooper.
New London County was the center of religious dissent in the colony and the records contain more than 150 cases concerning religious dissenters, be they Anglicans, Baptists, Rogerenes, Separatists, or Shakers, or adherents of the established Congregational Church, some 130 from before the American Revolution.78 Except for the Rogerene cases, researchers have not examined the bulk of these materials.79 The number of cases declines after the American Revolution, but a few interesting ones still merit attention.
Baptists and Separatists were not as good as Congregationalists in keeping records, therefore, the documentation found in court records, although scattered in nature, provides significant new information on these often shadowy groups.80
Many of the earliest cases found in Files concern the Rogerenes. In the first such case in 1698, James Rogers, founder of the sect, was accused of defaming the Reverend Gurdon Saltonstall of New London. "Said John Rogers did Sometime in the month of June last past, Raise a lying false and Scandalous Report, against... Saltonstall, and did publish the Same in the hearing of divers persons." The jury awarded Saltonstall £600 damages.81 The bulk of cases involving Rogerenes occurred prior to 1726, but one interesting one appears in the records of the February 1786 court session by which time adherents of the tiny sect called themselves Quakers, John Waterhouse and wife Elizabeth v. John Rogers, 2d, in a case of assault upon Elizabeth. The defendant claimed that the couple were not legally married, but the plaintiffs replied that they had been wed on December 2, 1770 "according to the forms and Ceremonies which their religious faith required" and produced a copy of the marriage certificate.82